Finding Aid for Campbell family papers, 1860-1865 and 1879-1949
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Campbell family papers 1860-1865, 1879-1949
Campbell family.
2 linear feet
85891 Aa 2
Ypsilanti and Ann Arbor, Michigan, area family; correspondence, diaries, and other family materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mary A. Campbell (donor no. 5189 ); diaries of William and Robert Campbell were donated by William J. Mundus (donor no. 10160 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Campbell family were early settlers to Augusta Township, Washtenaw County, Michigan. William Campbell, born December 1821 in Ayrshire, Scotland, had accompanied his parents to Michigan in 1841 where they settled on a farm. He graduated from the state normal school in Ypsilanti (now Eastern Michigan University) and became a school teacher and later a school principal. William Campbell was also instrumental in the founding of the Farmers and Mechanics Trade Association and its store. William Campbell would later purchase land on the then outskirts of Ann Arbor and return to farming as a livelihood. His son, Robert Clair Campbell, was born on August 25, 1870 in Ypsilanti, Michigan. He attended public schools in Ypsilanti but following the move of the family to Ann Arbor, he would graduate from Ann Arbor High School. Robert C. Campbell graduated from the University of Michigan in 1894 with a bachelor of science degree. He then went into the hardwood lumbering business in Wayne County but then returned to the family farm in 1901. In 1902, he married Carrie Read, of Pittsfield Township, a school teacher. She also had attended the University of Michigan. Robert C. Campbell died April 18, 1945.
The Campbell family collection includes correspondence and other family materials. Items of interest include Civil War correspondence of Gabriel Campbell and John S. Farnill; correspondence, diaries, and teaching materials of William Campbell; personal correspondence of Mary and Sarah (Sadie) Campbell concerning farming, local Republican politics, and school affairs; and printed materials concerning the Free Silver question and the election of 1896. The papers of Robert C. Campbell include diaries and University of Michigan student notebooks. Of interest are the notes he took from the lectures of John Dewey in philosophy, Henry Carter Adams in political economy, Burke A. Hinsdale in pedagogy, Joseph B. Steere in zoology, and A.A. Stanley in music, among other professors. The collection also includes high school notebooks of Carrie Read and E. Mabel Read.
Subjects:
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Agriculture--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor High School (Mich.)--Students.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Farm life--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Hinsdale, B. A. (Burke Aaron), 1837-1900.; Johnson, Lorenzo Nickerson, d.1897.; Lloyd, Alfred H. (Alfred Henry), 1864-1927.; Mead, George Herbert, 1863-1931.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; Presidents--United States--Election--1896.; Reighard, Jacob, 1861-1942; Republican Party (Mich.); Schools--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Silver question.; Spalding, Volney Morgan, 1849-1918.; Stanley, Albert A. (Albert Augustus), 1851-1932.; Steere, Joseph Beal, 1842-1940.; Taylor, F. M. (Fred Manville), 1855-1932.; Teachers--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1893-1897.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; Ward, Henry Baldwin, 1865-1945.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Ypsilanti (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Campbell family.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Michigan--Social life and customs--20th century.
Subjects: Visual Materials
Campbell family.; Carriages and coaches.; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Dwellings.; First Presbyterian Church (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Holidays.; Interiors.; Muskegon (Mich.); Parades and processions.; Photography.; Pinckney (Mich.); Recreation.; State Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Stone School (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Contributors:
Campbell, Robert Clair, 1870-1945.; Campbell, William, b.1829.; Read, Carrie.; Read, E. Mabel.
Genre Terms:
Cyanotypes.; Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1860-1865 (Box 1)
  - 1879-1889 (Box 1)
  - 1896-1897 (Box 1)
  - 1898, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900-1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1908-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1926 (Box 1)
  - 1927-1949 (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
- William Campbell
  - Diaries, 1882-1897 (some gaps), 12 volumes (Box 1)
  - Bank book 1892-1907 (Box 1)
- Robert C. Campbell
  - Diary-Account books, 1892 1893, 1894, 1899, 4 volumes (Box 1)
  - High school course notes (probably Ann Arbor High School): geometry and chemistry (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan course notes 1891-1894, 16 volumes
    - Combined volume 1891: Botany (V.M. Spalding); Zoology (J.E. Reighard), Zoology (J.B. Steere) (Box 2)
    - Biology 1893: Zoology (Ward) and Botany (Johnson) (Box 2)
    - Political economy (H.C. Adams) 1892 (Box 2)
    - Political philosophy (John Dewey 1893, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Pedagogy course 1 (B.A. Hinsdale) 1892 (Box 2)
    - Pedagogy 2 1894 (Box 2)
    - Pedagogy (B.A. Hinsdale) 1892 (Box 2)
    - Pedagogy (Hinsdale) 1893 (Box 2)
    - Political economy 2 (Taylor) 1894 (Box 2)
    - Spanish exercises 1892 (Box 2)
    - Qualitative chemical analysis (Box 2)
    - Philosophy (Mead) 1893 (Box 2)
    - Philosophy -- British ethics (Lloyd) 1892 (Box 2)
    - Music course (Stanley) (Box 2)
- Other Material
  - E. Mabel Read (Ann Arbor High School)
    - Physical laboratory notebooks, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Chemical laboratory (Box 2)
  - Carrie E. Read (Ann Arbor High School)
    - Ann Arbor High School physical laboratory notebooks, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Botany (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - School essays (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 2 envelopes (Box 2)
    (includes pictures of family homes, schools, churches, outings, a parade and carriages)
  - Diary (unidentified), 1946 (Box 2)